

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research aims to improve how people manage, understand, and reuse both code and data through the design of new programming languages and visualization tools. By focusing new languages and tools on the domain-specific details relevant to the user, we can improve how users interact with the system to better promote program understanding, and proactively surface surprising or incorrect results.

EDUCATION

2016 - present PhD Candidate Computer Science and Engineering

SEATTLE, WA Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

University of Washington (UW)

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer

2016 MS COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

University of Washington (UW)

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer

2014 BS COMPUTER SCIENCE

CLAREMONT, CA Harvey Mudd College (HMC)

Advisor: Ben Wiedermann

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SEATTLE, WA

2014 - present Graduate Research Assistant, UW Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

Languages and Visualization Tools for Data-Centric End User Programming of Interactive Visualizations. Advisor: Jeffrey Heer. Conducted research on the design and development of new systems and program understanding techniques for visualization design. Conducted interviews with

experts to inform research directions and performed user evaluations of the proposed systems.

Summer 2019 RESEARCH INTERN, ADOBE RESEARCH

SEATTLE, WA Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design

Advisors: Leo Zhicheng Liu and Wilmot Li. Conducted research on the design of responsive visualizations for news articles, which adapt the visualization to different types of devices.

Summer 2018 RESEARCH INTERN, ADOBE RESEARCH

SEATTLE, WA Interactive Repair of Tables Extracted from PDF Documents on Mobile Devices

Advisor: Leo Zhicheng Liu. Conducted research on the future of dynamic PDF documents, focusing on the analysis & reuse of tabular data for dynamic applications on mobile devices.

Summer 2013 UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA Visualizing the Graphical Execution of Abstract Program Traces

Advisor: Ben Wiedermann. Modified the UC Santa Barbara JavaScript Abstract Interpreter to output runtime information about the abstract program trace and implemented a tool for

visualizing program traces using D3.js.

Summer 2012 Undergraduate Research Assistant, HMC Computer Science Department

CLAREMONT, CA Large Scale, Educational Video Games for Middle School Students

Advisor: Elizabeth Sweedyk. Developed a math-based game for the iPad that teaches children about ratios by taking advantage of the ratio-based behavior of mixing paint.

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

HONORS AND AWARDS

2020 ACM CHI Best Paper Award (for "Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design")

2019 ACM CHI 2019 Doctoral Consortium Award

Hopper x 1 Seattle 2019 Scholarship Award Recipient

2014 Jeff Dean - Heidi Hopper Endowed Regental Fellowship Recipient

Harvey Mudd College Computer Science Clinic Poster Award

Honorable Mention CRA Undergraduate Research Award Competition

2011-2014 Harvey Mudd College Dean's List

2010 International Baccalaureate Diploma

PUBLICATIONS

2020 Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design.

Jane Hoffswell, Wilmot Li, and Zhicheng Liu.

CHI 2020. TO APPEAR: doi.org/10.1145/3313831.3376777

[24% Acceptance Rate, Best Paper Award (Top 1%)]

2019 Interactive Repair of Tables Extracted from PDF Documents on Mobile Devices.

Jane Hoffswell and Zhicheng Liu.

CHI 2019. doi.org/10.1145/3290605.3300523

[24% Acceptance Rate]

2018 SetCoLa: High-Level Constraints for Graph Layout.

Jane Hoffswell, Alan Borning, Jeffrey Heer.

Euro Vis 2018. doi.org/10.1111/cgf.13440

[29% Acceptance Rate]

Augmenting Code with In Situ Visualizations to Aid Program Understanding.

Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

CHI 2018. doi.org/10.1145/3173574.3174106

[26% Acceptance Rate]

Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers using Food and Symptom Journals. Jessica Schroeder, **Jane Hoffswell**, Chia-Fang Chung, James Fogarty, Sean Munson, Jasmine Zia.

CSCW 2017. doi.org/10.1145/2998181.2998276

[35% Acceptance Rate]

2016 Visual Debugging Techniques for Reactive Data Visualization.

Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

Euro Vis 2016. doi.org/10.1111/cgf.12903

[27% Acceptance Rate]

Reactive Vega: A Streaming Dataflow Architecture for Declarative Interactive Visualization.

Arvind Satyanarayan, Ryan Russell, **Jane Hoffswell**, Jeffrey Heer.

InfoVis 2016. doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467091

[22% Acceptance Rate]

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

Spring 2019 LANGUAGES & VISUALIZATIONS TO ENABLE EFFECTIVE END USER PROGRAMMING.

GLASGOW, UK Jane Hoffswell.

CHI Extended Abstracts 2019. doi.org/10.1145/3290607.3299067

Spring 2015 Debugging Vega through Inspection of the Data Flow Graph.

Cagliari, Italy Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

Euro Vis Workshop on Reproducibility, Verification, and Validation in Visualization (EuroRV3), 2015.

doi.org/10.2312/eurorv3.20151144

POSTERS

Spring 2019 LANGUAGES & VISUALIZATIONS TO ENABLE EFFECTIVE END USER PROGRAMMING.

GLASGOW, UK ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems Doctoral Consortium Poster, 2019.

Fall 2016 VISUAL DEBUGGING TECHNIQUES FOR REACTIVE DATA VISUALIZATION.

SEATTLE, WA University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates, 2016.

TALKS

Spring 2020 Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design.

SEATTLE, WA DUB Shorts, University of Washington. SCHEDULED: dub.washington.edu/seminars/2020-05-06.html

Spring 2020 How People Understand Systems.

SEATTLE, WA UW Allen School Women's Research Day. https://youtu.be/EJtakt7I3BQ

Spring 2014 VISUALIZING THE GRAPHICAL EXECUTION OF PROGRAMS FOR JAVASCRIPT ABSTRACT INTERPRETATION.

SAN DIEGO, CA Southern California Celebration for Women in Computing.

Fall 2013 VISUALIZING THE GRAPHICAL EXECUTION OF PROGRAMS FOR JAVASCRIPT ABSTRACT INTERPRETATION.

Los Angeles, CA Southern California Programming Languages and Systems Workshop.

Summer 2012 HARVEY MUDD COLLEGE NASA UNIVERSITY STUDENT LAUNCH INITIATIVE TEAM PRESENTATION.

Santa Ana, CA AIAA Southern California Aerospace Systems and Technology (ASAT) Conference.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2016-2017 TEACHING ASSISTANT, UW PAUL. G. ALLEN SCHOOL OF COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA CSE442 (Spring 2017) and CSE512 (Spring 2016) — Data Visualization. Professor: Jeffrey Heer

Graded coursework, held office hours, and taught extra tutorial sessions.

Winter 2014 TEACHING ASSISTANT, UW MASTERS IN HUMAN COMPUTER INTERACTION + DESIGN

SEATTLE, WA HCID520 (Spring 2014) - User Interface Software & Technology. Professor: Jeffrey Heer

Helped to develop the course curriculum. Tutored and graded coursework.

2012-2014 TUTOR AND GRADER, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA CS131 – Programming Languages (Spring 2014). Professor: Melissα O'Neill

CS151 — Artificial Intelligence (Spring 2014).

CS121 — Software Development (Fall 2013).

CS121 — Software Development (Spring 2013).

Professor: Jim Boerkoel

Professor: Mike Erlinger

Professor: Elizabeth Sweedyk

CS60 - Principles of Computer Science (Fall 2012). Professor: Zach Dodds

Graded coursework and held office hours.

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

LEADERSHIP AND VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

2018 - present Grad, VGrad, & Postdoc Advisory Council, UW Computer Science & Engineering

SEATTLE, WA Participated as a council member of the G5PAC to discuss and address the needs of

researchers and teaching assistants in the Paul G. Allen School.

Winter 2020 PRACTICE TALKS SEMINAR ORGANIZER (CSE591L), UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

Seattle, WA Organized and lead a new weekly seminar focused on presenting and providing feedback

on practice talks from graduate students in the Paul G. Allen School.

2017 - present **REVIEWER**

ACM CHI - ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems 2017, 2019-2020

IEEE VIS - IEEE Visualization 2018-2019
ACM UIST - ACM User Interface Software and Technology 2017-2019
IEEE TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 2018

Recognition for Outstanding Reviews: CHI 2019

Winter 2018 HCI VISIT DAYS COORDINATOR, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

 ${}^{\text{SEATTLE, WA}} \quad \text{Organized group activities and one-on-one meetings for admitted graduate students.}$

Fall 2016 GRADUATE STUDENT ADMISSIONS VOLUNTEER, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Reviewed graduate student admissions applications.

Fall 2015 New Graduate Orientation Leader, UW Computer Science & Engineering

SEATTLE, WA Coordinated talks from current students and faculty for incoming graduate students,

organized activities for the event, and hosted the two-day orientation.

2013-2014 PROJECT MANAGER, CAPSTONE PROJECT, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA Visualizing and Exploring Performance Data alongside VMware

Advisor: Melissa O'Neill. Acted as project manager for a senior capstone project with

VMware in which we developed a dashboard for visualizing system performance using D3.js.

Fall 2015 Project Manager, USLI Rocketry Team, Harvey Mudd College

CLAREMONT, CA Founder and project manager of a NASA sponsored rocketry team for the University

Student Launch Initiative (USLI). Designed and launched a rocket with a scientific payload.

RELEVANT SKILLS

Coding: JavaScript, Python, HTML/CSS, D3.js, Vega/Vega-Lite

User Research: Semi-Structured Interviews, Surveys, Experimental Design

Leadership: Project Management, Scientific & Technical Writing, Presentations

Tools: GitHub, Tableau, LaTeX, Keynote, Microsoft Excel, OmniGraffle

GRADUATE COURSEWORK

2019 Research Methods and Data Analysis in Software Systems Research

2017 Accurate Computing · Constraint Programming

2016 Advanced Topics in HCI · Computer-Aided Reasoning for Software · Research Design

2015 Computer Systems · Data Visualization · Principles of Database Management Systems

2014 Machine Learning